Guide to the Michael Alexander Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Michael Alexander papers
1959-2013
YCAL MSS 1098
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.52
(6 boxes)
The papers document the personal and professional life of Michael Alexander, professor, translator, and editor, who focused on Ezra Pound's works and his influence during his career. The collection includes submission drafts for Alexander's book, The Sons of Ezra: British Poets and Ezra Pound; correspondence with writers and colleagues including Ezra Pound, Peter Whigham, and Peter Russell; and publication information for The Sons of Ezra. Also included are papers pertaining to Alexander's role as associate editor at Agenda; Alexander's research files on Pound and his influences; typescripts of Peter Whigham's poetry; and an outline for an edition of Cantullus's "LXIV."
Alexander, Michael, 1941-
Scope and Contents
The papers document the personal and professional life of Michael Alexander, who focused on Ezra Pound's works and influence on other writers during his career. The collection includes submission drafts for Alexander's book, The Sons of Ezra: British Poets and Ezra Pound; correspondence with writers and other colleagues including Ezra Pound, Peter Whigham, and Peter Russell; and publication information for The Sons of Ezra. Also included are papers pertaining to Alexander's role as associate editor at Agenda; Alexander's research files on Pound and his influences; typescripts of Peter Whigham's poetry; and an outline for an English translation by Whigham of Catullus's Epithalamium pelei et Thetidos.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Michael Alexander (1941-), English professor at St. Andrew's College and editor. Alexander was the co-editor of The Sons of Ezra: British Poets and Ezra Pound (Amsterdam, Neth.: Rodopi, 1995) with James McGonigal. Alexander was also an associate editor at Agenda, a literary magazine founded by Ezra Pound and William Cookson in 1959.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: Series I. Correspondence, 1959-2013. Series II. Editorial Work, 1985-2003. Series III. Ezra Pound Related Materials, 1963-2013. Series IV. Books, 1957-1990.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Joan Winterkorn on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund and the Ezra Pound Archive Fund, 2016.
Agenda (London, England); Editors -- Great Britain; Poets, English -- 20th Century; Editors -- United Kingdom -- 20th Century; Joan Winterkorn; Alexander, Michael, 1941-; Cookson, William, 1939-; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Russell, Peter, 1921-2003; Whigham, Peter; University of St. Andrews. Department of English
- Correspondence, 1959-2013; Series I; 0.84 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes correspondence between Alexander and his colleagues, friends, and relatives.
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The folder contents are in chronological order.
  - A general, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B general, 1983-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - C general, 1962-2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cookson, William, 1978-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - D general, 1966-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - E general, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - F general, 1973-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - G general, 1969-2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - H general, 1964-2011 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - I-J general, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - K-L general, 1963-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - M general, 1963-1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - N-O general, 1963-2005 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pound, Dorothy, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pound, Ezra, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - P general (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rudge, Olga, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - R general, 1965-2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - S general, 1967-1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - T general, 1966-1998 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - W general, 1976-1999 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Whigham, Peter, 1959-2013 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - X-Z general, 1966-1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Editorial Work, 1985-2003; Series II; 0.84 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series II contains major works edited by Alexander: Agenda magazine and "The Sons of Ezra: British Poets and Ezra Pound."
  Series II is arranged in the way in which it was recieved by the library.
  - Agenda #1, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Agenda #1, 1985-1991 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Agenda #2, 1985-2003 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Agenda #2, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Sons of Ezra #1, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Sons of Ezra #1, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Sons of Ezra #1, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Sons of Ezra #2, 1991-1995 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Sons of Ezra #3, 1993-2000 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Sons of Ezra #2, 1990-1995 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Sons of Ezra #2, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Sons of Ezra #3, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Sons of Ezra #3, 1991- 1993 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Ezra Pound Related Materials, 1963-2013; Series III; 0.42 linear feet (1 box)
  Series III is arranged in groups by subject.
  Series III contains materials about Ezra Pound and Pound scholarship. It also includes information from a conference on Pound and drafts of Peter Whigham's poetry. The conference, the Ezra Pound International Conference, was hosted by the Institute of English Studies and held at the University of London, Senate House in July, 2011.
  - Miscellaneous Ezra Pound materials, 1963-1989 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous Ezra Pound materials, 1980-1995 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Ezra Pound Conference, Whigham correspondence, and Whigham manuscript, 1964-2013 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Books, 1957-1990; Series IV; 0.42 linear feet (1 box)
  This series contains books owned by Michael Alexander. Many of the books are collections of poetry written or edited by his colleagues Peter Russell and Peter Whigham. Some books have dedications; The Worth Record, Summer Term 1962 is annotated.
  Series IV is arranged by title.
  - The European, 1957 (Box 6)
  - Forgotten Kingdom by Peter Goullart, 1957 (Box 6)
  - The Worth Record, 1960 (Box 6)
  - The Worth Record, 1961 (Box 6)
  - The Worth Record, 1961 (Box 6)
  - The Worth Record, 1962 (Box 6)
  - The Worth Record, 1962 (Box 6)
  - The Worth Record, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Arion edited by Thomas Gould, 1965 (Box 6)
  - The Blue Winged Bee by Peter Whigham, 1969 (Box 6)
  - The Poems of Meleager edited by Peter Jay, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Things Common, Properly: Selected Poems 1942-1980 by Peter Whigham, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Fragments of a Life by Moelwyn Merchant, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Teorie E Altre Liriche, undated (Box 6)
  - The Marriage Rite by Peter Whigham and Denis Groacher, undated (Box 6)